Not having success is not an option. Like I have to succeed.
It's basically a matter of existence, a survival of my family.
When you want to change a certain habit,
science says it takes at least 21 days,
right? For the brain to start growing you know, new neurons that are
reprogramming. But if you don't have the right
environment, that's going to be very,
very challenging. The environment is the
one that can be very stimulative to you. It can be really supportive or
it can be pulling you down. So it's super important, even though we
we always encourage ourselves to be
independent in terms of what we do, what
we eat, how we sleep, how you know, how
we lead our lives and what we do and how
we can live the best version of our
lives possible, but at the same time, we
are social beings. We are very tribal beings. And even if it's the smallest
community, we still want to belong to that community. We still want this
community to support us, even if it's one person, too.
But it's super important in the end of
the day because, you know, making tough choices These are tough choices
cause society when you go out there, you know, super majority of the places
where you go to eat or people that you see, it's a kind of a
vicious cycle and they lead their life in a certain way that maybe doesn't
coincide or correspond to your choices
that you want to make, the new choices
or maybe the new changes. So it's really
hard. I feel like it's it's reinventing
yourself constantly, you know, for me,
I've had this kind of upbringing, had a great foundation. And,
you know, I have achieved incredible things. I was dreaming of becoming
number one in the world and becoming a Wimbledon champion.
And that was my dream. I achieved that
dream within 2 days. I won Wimbledon and at the same and same day became
number one in the world. It's just you know, once-in-a-lifetime type of
experience. And when you do something for the first
time, obviously that big, it's just like
you're you're flying to the moon. I mean, you're not you it's a kind of an
old out-of-body experience. So, of course, it was kind of a surreal
experience for me and I tried to enjoy
it and embrace it, but at the same time
I felt like, "Okay, it's great to share
the court with these guys, but I want to
beat them. You know, I want to get the
biggest titles. I want to be number one.
I want to dominate." So, I think that
the first kind of that wave that I was riding on
helped me to win my first slam when I was 19. I I won couple of big
tournaments and so forth. I reached number two in the world. But, you know,
I still wasn't number one. And then I I
had a 3-year period I didn't win a slam.
I was winning some big tournaments, but I couldn't win a slam.
These two guys were beating me in every
big match, Federer and Nadal. I changed rackets
you know, team members. I I I did everything I can to kind of find the the
right formula. And I was struggling physically
as well. I wasn't you know, that's where
actually I had my transformative journey
nutrition-wise where I took everything started going in the in the upwards
direction for me and learning also from these guys and the matches
that we've played against each other was
something that was extremely important for me at the time. I was, of
course, trying to consume as much as I can this energy of
the center court and everything. And it was overwhelming at times,
but I was also very thorough in my analysis of the matches afterwards,
even though I don't necessarily like to watch matches that I lost, but
you know, Kobe Bryant used to talk about this a lot and I when
I was talking to him personally about that, he would and he said,
"Even if it's just specific intervals of the match that you lost
that you want to watch, that you definitely look at that and you need to
analyze that and you need to go through that cramping feeling
because that's where you learn from those those mistakes and that's
where you have an opportunity to rectify that the next next tournament or
next match and so forth. So, that helped a lot.
I have identified that as well is my feeling of not being enough.
And that goes back to my very very beginning of my life and my relationship
particularly with my father. And not being not doing enough, not
being good enough, etc. etc. So, and it's kind of the battle that I that
I also go through often. Cuz a lot of people even closest people
in my life ask me, you know, what more
do you want? You know, you have achieved everything.
What do you want? What why why do you
keep going? And I tell them the the good
part that I told you that I still really
strongly feel it's inside of me and I and I feel like as long as I have the
capacity or ability to compete for the biggest
titles in our in my sport, I want to keep going.
And also partly the part that I didn't mention
that inspires me to keep going is to test my limits
mentally and physically. Cuz when I was starting to break through
in the professional tennis, I remember when you reach your 30, you
start counting your days to your retirement. Like after 30, you know,
that's it pretty much. It's also a a kind of a a curiosity from
my side of how how far can I go? You know, I'm I'm 38 this year. You know,
how long can I push my own limits? And I don't feel like I do have
a limits. And I feel like the limits are normally constructs in our mind.
I've seen the episode you did with the
Brian Johnson the other day. And then he talked about, you know, he's
by a lot of people's opinion very extreme.
But you know, he dedicated his own entire life to
getting the data and understanding what
are the best conditions for the longest living life that he can have for
himself. Which I think it's something that is admirable and you know,
I give him huge credit for that. And it
I understand because as a professional athlete, you know, the care for your
body and your mind and the devotion to the daily habits is so tough.
That's where it started and I was like I was really
trying to adapt all of the great things
that I could see. And I have a kind of a photogenic memory and I'm a very a
visual person. And that was something
that was kind of expected, that is kind
of common as well what you do with kids,
you know, or or with young athletes,
right? You watch videotapes, you try to analyze, try to talk.
But you know, so it taught me to really
understand that tennis is not only about
hitting a tennis ball over the net and counting score and dreaming
about these achievements and winning Wimbledon as our uh, holy grail of
tennis. But it's it's more than that.
And and I can use tennis as a platform to evolve into a better human being.
At that point, I didn't understand that.
But then as I was growing older and becoming more mature, I I start to
understand the importance of doing all of these practices. And I
started to expand in each of these topics that that I was going
through with her. So, I'm very curious by nature. So, I
was really always looking for new ways
to improve myself and improve my life on this planet, you know?
And I was very lucky to be basically have that space also from my parents.
It's a kind of a self-discovery through the self-care, through tennis
really consumed most of my life. But I'm
still surprising and shocking myself on
how much I actually need to still work
on that and I still  don't know enough about that world.
And it was really hard for me to accept
that. You know, I thought, you know,
since 10, I basically started working on
that and and growing the foundation, but it has evolved and has
transformed so much for me in terms of how I see myself, how
I see the world. And I thought, you know, maybe when I
was at at the peak of my career and, you know, I felt like I'm unbeatable
and I feel I feel like I could do anything. You know, I kind of walking on
the water. We all experience that in in in our own lives in certain way
and it's a great feeling. But then the ego takes you places where
it's it's hard to come back from. And
maybe you shouldn't come back from that. Maybe you you're trying to find a
balance, find the optimal measure that
really works for you, but it it took me time to really accept the fact that
what I have learned, what I have mastered
and what I'm doing on a daily basis for the last 20 years or more
is not necessarily a guarantee that I'll
always find a way and that will always
work for me in this particular time of my life and circumstances that I'm
facing. So that's a huge revelation for
me because and I'm still trying to get a grasp on it and and understand
all of these factors that are in play
that are challenging me on a daily basis and
when I talk from this perspective, it's
a beautiful journey that I'm trying to
embrace, but when you are immersed in
the dark moment, it's it's kind of hard
to to really get out of that. But also, other athletes and how,
you know, the struggles they had mentally and particularly the struggles
that they had if they have not prepared themselves for that transition. I
believe that in some way you cannot fully prepare yourself for that
transition mentally. Like, it's going to
be a sad day for me when I leave tennis and it's going to be very
emotional and all that. But what I'm talking about is basically
the adrenaline. That also needs to be filtered
or re-channeled somewhere. And I know that I will play sports for the
rest of my life cuz I love sports and being active is essential.
But also, I feel like you need a challenge. Tennis has consumed most of
my life and that's what I know how to do best.
But I have very broad interest in a lot
of different things and the industry or the the sphere of of life
which is called health, wellness, and well-being is
my biggest passion and it's very broad
ecosystem or field, if if you want, as you know, because you're part of it.
But it has been my passion for 15 plus years and
you know, uh always imagine the world where
most of the people will take care of themselves of, you know, how they
hydrate, how they eat, exercise, how they manage their sleep.
Just a healthier world. And of course, it's it's harder
change everything at the same time and it of course takes a lot of
different time cuz this planet is big and there's a lot of people, but
I take taking small steps is very valuable and it has its effect.
And the idea is that you're always on a battlefield and as you said, on the
battlefield, you see the best of yourself and the worst of yourself. And
often people said that to me when I moved to LA, everyone's like, "Why do
you want to be in LA? There's so much materialism, there's so much,
you know, illusion here." And I said,
"Well, actually, I feel like I'm on the
battlefield here. So, I see the best of
myself and I see the worst of myself."
And the worst of myself reminds me to keep going and to keep working on
myself. And the best of myself allows me
to share my message with the biggest megaphone in the world. And so, it's
that dichotomy of actually, when you're looking for
spiritual growth, you want to be in a place that reminds you of your
weaknesses as much as your strength.
Because if you are only reminded of your
strength, you just have your ego. And if you were only reminded of your
weaknesses, well, then you would be depressed or disheartened.
But son, it's okay to be bored sometimes. First of all, you had a great
active morning and you did a lot of things. Second of all, you know, when
you are bored, it doesn't mean that you have to instantly take a book
or a screen or anything else. You need to also learn how to be with
your thoughts. And if you are not comfortable being
bored indoors, go outdoors. Sit on a
chair and have have some drink and just look at the sky.
And I And I think that's much easier said than done.
And I And I I really would love my my children to to be able to be
okay with being bored because that's the
time when you're actually most creative
or that's the time when you can manage
your thoughts and everything that you have been suppressing by distracting
yourself with phone, with whatever it
is. You know, it's it's a struggle, but
it's important. You know, I think it's
super important, particularly for them at this young age to
I think that it has been talked about a lot. Yeah, I agree.
Uh on a how Why is it that our sports are so popular? Why is it that
people relate to athletes? It's because
of this grit, because of this battle. We
all go through internal battle on daily
basis and in sports we can, of course, admire the the features of
an athlete and the skills and the talent
and the abilities, but at the same time
we also identify ourselves with those athletes. We we feel like
wow, you know, that this game or a match
it's in a way a condensed daily life or a condensed life into an hour or
two or three where you you start at the beginning
you're even, then you end up, you know,
winning or losing, but in the process our journey of the match and the game
you're going through ups and downs. You're going and particularly in
individual sports you're going You mentioned Lewis Hamilton,
another great legend. You're going through that battle of, you
know, trying to win that inner battle
where you go through your doubts, your worries, your fears.
So, all of these of elements are part of everyday life of everyday person.
And that's why I feel like people relate
to sports. And they also they they when
they go to see sport live, particularly,
but also when they watch it on TV, I feel they're able because they
they are so connected to the community
of that club or that athlete or whatever it is,
they feel like all of their problems stop at least for those hour two three
hours that they are watching. Where they feel like they can
free themselves of the emotions and the
burdens that are kind of wearing them
down. But I can see that there's a lot of people that are like
That's why That's why like after a game
they either feel drained or they feel energized. They either feel like they
have kind of like collected that energy from
the stadium or they feel like they're completely like a deflated balloon.